Guide to the Hispanic Apparel Union Officers Oral History Collection OH.004
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Hispanic Apparel Union Officers Oral History Collection
1983-1984
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Fox, Geoffrey E.
OH.004
1 Linear Feet in 1 compact disk box, 1 manuscript box, and 1 card catalog drawer.
The collection is comprised of interviews with 26 organizers, which were conducted by Geoffrey Fox as part of a study entitled "Hispanic Organizers and Business Agents." The study was published as an occasional paper of New York University's Center for Latin American and Caribbean Studies in 1984. It explored how Hispanic immigrants were assimilated into labor organizations and how they, in the process, adapted and reformed these organizations for themselves. Interviewees were mostly members of the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union and the International Ladies' Garment Workers Union. Except for four New York-born Puerto Ricans, all interviewees are immigrants from Latin America, including: Puerto Rico, the Dominican Republic, Costa Rica, Ecuador, Chile, and Honduras. Interviewees discuss their careers, experiences in the industry and unions, organizing methods, and views on the labor movement.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Geoffrey Fox in 1984. The accession number associated with this collection is 1950.132.
Arrangement
Access compact disks, transcripts, and interview notes are arranged alphabetically by interviewee. Master cassettes are arranged by an an assigned numbering scheme.
Historical/Biographical Note
The interviews were conducted by Fox as part of a study entitled "Hispanic Organizers and Business Agents," published as an occasional paper of New York University's Center for Latin American and Caribbean Studies in 1984. The study explored how Hispanic immigrants were assimilated into labor organizations and how they, in the process, adapted and reformed these organizations for themselves.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of interviews in English and Spanish with 26 organizers, most of whom worked for the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union and the International Ladies' Garment Workers Union. Except for four New York-born Puerto Ricans, all interviewees are immigrants from Latin America, including: Puerto Rico, the Dominican Republic, Costa Rica, Ecuador, Chile, and Honduras. Interviewees discuss their careers, experiences in the industry and unions, organizing methods, and views on the labor movement. Additionally, there is one box of transcripts and interview notes, which also contains Geoffrey E. Fox's "Hispanic Organizers and Business Agents in the New York Apparel Industries," a paper derived from the interviews.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Working class |x Organizing.; Oral histories (literary works); Immigrants -- New York (N.Y.); Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z New York.; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
- Kathy Andrade, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 1, Box 1, Cd Andrade 1, Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 21)
  Historical/Biographical Note
  Union colonizer, organizer.
  Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
- Sandy Bermejo, Dec 8, 1983 (Box 1, Cd Bermejo 1, Box 2, Folder 2, Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 1)
  Headwear Joint Board, business agent.
- José Berríos, Dec 8, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 3, Box 1, Cd Berrios 1-2, Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 2)
  District 65 organizer, Headwear Joint Board, Hatters Union.
- Enio Carrion, undated (Box 1, Cd Carrion 1, Box 2, Folder 4, Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 3)
  UFWA organizer, local business agent, secretary treasurer, president, AFL/CIO.
- Ernesto Castillo, Rosa Mejias, and Julia Pietri, Jan 9, 1984 (Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 4B, Box 1, Cd Castillo, Mejias, Pietri 1, Box 2, Folder 5, 19, 22)
- Delores Dávila and Juan Laboriel, Dec 8, 1983 and Dec 9, 1983 (Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 5B, Box 1, Cd Davila and Laboriel 1-2, Box 2, Folder 6)
  ACTWU 169 council member, vice-president, chair, claims department, business agent.
- Edwin Espaillat, Mar 25, 1983 (Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 6, Box 1, Cassette Espaillat 1, Box 2, Folder 8)
  Flight engineer, ACT union founder, AFT local chair, HCL secretary, LCLAA vice-president, AIFLD teacher.
- Pascual Fonseca, Jan 12, 1984 (Box 1, Cd Fonseca 1, Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 7, Box 2, Folder 9)
  Scope and Content Note
  Experience as factory union organizer, balancing personal and professional lives.
- Geoffrey Fox, "Hispanic Organizers and Business Agents in the New York Apparel Industries.", Apr 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Manuel (Manny) Gonzalez, Jan 4, 1984 (Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 8, Box 1, Cd Gonzales 1, Box 2, Folder 11)
  ILGWU Local 22: Head of Education Department, organizer, executive board, secretary-manager, vice-president ILGWU.
- Emigdio Hernández and Abraham Escobar, Jan 11, 1984 (Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 9, Box 1, Cd Hernandez and Escobar 1, Box 2, Folder 7, 12)
- Ernesto Jofre, Mar 3, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 13, Box 1, Cd Joffre 1, Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 10)
  Discussion of Chilean labor unions, imprisonment, emigration, and experience as ACTWU organizer.
- Juan Laboriel, Dec 9, 1983 (Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 5A, Box 2, Folder 14, Box 1, Cd Laboriel 1)
  UFCW General Organizer.
- Wilfredo Larancuent, Nov 11, 1983 (Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 12, Box 2, Folder 15, Box 1, Cd Laracuent 1)
  Headwear Joint Board vice-president, ACTWU local 110 manager, Baby Bonnet Workers Union.
- Sonia Laracuente, Dec 13, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 16, Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 11, Box 1, Cd Laracuente 1)
  ILGWU local 40 translator, business agent, Red Cross CETA Program.
- Ernesto Macias, Maria Martinez, and Ernesto Castillo, Jan 9, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 5, 17-18, Box 1, Cd Macias, Martinez, Castillo 1-2, Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 13)
- Rosa Mejias, Jan 9, 1984 (Box 1, Cd Mejias 1, Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 4A)
  ILGWU local 66 Education Director, active in International Dept. Education.
- Lionel Otero and Luis Santiago, Jun 1, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20, Box 1, Cd Otero and Santiago 1-2, Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 14)
  ACWU Education Director, business agent, Amalgamated Services Joint Bd.
- Frank Perez, Jan 23, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 21, Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 15, Box 1, Cd Perez 1-2)
  Discussion of experiences as ILGWU local 132 delegate, organizer, Executive Board, and dismissal.
- Jose Prince, Mar 28, 1983 (Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 16, Box 1, Cd Prince 1-2, Box 2, Folder 23)
  Discussion of Cuban labor movement, CLAT rep. in U.S., Latin American labor movement.
- Aracelly Santana, Nov 17, 1983 (Box 1, Cd Santana 1, Box 2, Folder 24, Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 17)
  Discussion of experience as ILG business agent, corruption, sexism, and harassment in union.
- Ed Vargas, Dec 29, 1983 (Box 1, Cd Vargas 1, Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 18)
  ILG organizer.
- Olga Velasco, Jan 10, 1984 (Box 1, Cd Velasco 1, Box 2, Folder 26, Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 19)
  Organizer, ACTWU NY Joint Board.
- Roger Waldinger, Nov 18, 1983 (Box 1, Cd Waldinger 1-2, Box Shared Cassette Box 6, Cassette 20)
  "Immigrant Entrepreneurship in the New York Garment Industry"